petition, and we have five minutes set down for you to speak to that
this afternoon. I'll hand over to you.
Sounds good. Thank you.
I'm an Iranian Kiwi and a member of Free Iran Unity New Zealand,
the group that led this petition.
We recognize that there's no established precedent for an opposition leader to
address the parliament, and we are truly grateful for this opportunity.
However, there's clear international precedent for this kind of
engagement. This year alone, Prince Reza Pahlavi has
addressed Sweden's parliament and met with politicians and
parliament members in Italy, Germany, US,
Netherlands, UK, France, Ukraine,
Canada, and has recently been invited to visit
Australia.
More than 13,000 people have signed this petition,
asking the parliament to invite Prince Reza Pahlavi.
We're not asking parliament to support a particular political system or to
decide Iran's future. That decision belongs to the Iranian
people.
We're simply asking parliament to listen.
For 47 years, the Iranian people have lived under a
regime that has restricted basic freedoms,
suppressed opposition, and violated fundamental human
rights.
In January 2026, millions of Iranians across more than
200 cities responded to calls for unity and change.
The regime responded with an internet blackout,
unprecedented massacre, and mass repression.
Prince Reza Pahlavi's name has been chanted on the streets of Iran,
and he has become the most prominent opposition figure advocating for
democratic change in the country.
What happens in Iran also matters to New Zealand, education, nationality,
and security trade through the Hormuz and cost of living,
and it also matters a lot to New Zealand's Iranian community.
An address would give our elect representatives the opportunity to hear
directly from Iran's opposition leader, understand the
situation in Iran, and the possible pathways ahead.
Ultimately, this is about listening to those whose
voices have been silenced. It's about human rights, and
it's about democracy.
It's about giving New Zealand the opportunity to hear directly from
Iranians about a future that belongs to them.
Thank you.
Very good. Question, Simon Court.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you, Sana.
Thank you, Sherry and Rosa, and all of you who have
made such an effort to raise the plight of the Iranian
people with leaders in New Zealand.
I have a question for you about
what matters the
Crown Prince raised in his recent
engagements with political leaders that you think are
important for New Zealand parliamentarians to know.
And did any of that cover the actions of the Iranian government against
its people?
Yes, absolutely.
So the Crown Prince has been going around and talking to
politicians about what is happening in Iran to the people,
about everyday executions that are going on, about the
massacre that happened in January, and the world mostly remained
silent. But also about the future, about how the future
will look like, what the plan is,
what the prosperity project for Iran looks like, the framework that
they have worked on to move Iran
post-Islamic regime, and
for basically transition towards a democratic, secular
community.
And also forming connections and
collaborations with other countries and how the outlook will look like
with a free Iran.
So just for the supplementary, Mr. Chair.
Mm-hmm.
Did the Crown Prince suggest in any of his presentations to
other parliaments or
bodies
what democratic countries could do to support the people of Iran?
Yes. I think the most
important thing that the democratic countries can do
is to recognize the will and wish of the Iranian people for change,
and their wish to get rid of the Islamic regime in
Iran as the first step. To recognize that there is a
legitimate opposition and opposition leader that the people of Iran
are largely behind,
and support to go through the transition period
post the Islamic regime. So yeah, if the international community
can offer that recognition, and that is one of the things that the Crown
Prince has been asking for,
would help the Iranians in their fights
greatly.
Right. Question from Honorable Damien O'Connor.
Look, thank you very much. I'm just wondering, do you think that the recent
conflict has helped the Iranian people or not?
Recent conflict?
Yes. So what's happening is there is a killing machine in Iran.
In January, eighth and ninth of January, tens of thousands of people have
been massacred by the regime. The recent
conflict
made the ground level for Iranian people by disarming the
killing machine. Yes, it helped the Iranian people by
saving more lives. If those conflict wouldn't have been placed,
certainly there would be hundreds of thousands of Iranian people would have been
massacred by this regime.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you very much for your time today.
Really appreciate you
sending the petition first of all, and then speaking to it today.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Right.